Monisha Gopalan

Address Via Giambellino 22, 35129, Padova, Italy.

E-mail moni2996@gmail.com **Mobile** +39 3491897796

Date of Birth29 December 1996NationalityIndian

LinkedIn https://www.linkedin.com/in/monisha-gopalan/

Website https://monishagopalan.github.io/



SUMMARY

As an enthusiastic AI Scientist Intern at an AI startup, I bring a strong academic background with double masters in STEM, majoring in physics, and diverse interdisciplinary research experience. I specialize in Portfolio Optimization in Finance and have a solid grasp of the deep learning methods and statistics. I'm actively pursuing opportunities as an AI/Data Scientist.

SKILLS

Programming	 - Python (advanced) – NumPy, Pandas, PyTorch, SciPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-learn - SQL - (basic) MATLAB, R, C 		
IT Skills	- AWS Sagemaker - Linux Terminal		- VS Code - Microsoft Office – Word, Excel, PowerPoint
Certifications	 Data Analysis with Python – freeCodeCamp - March 2023. Quantitative Finance with R – Udemy – July 2023. Introduction to Portfolio Construction and Analysis with Python – Coursera – April 2023. 		
Soft skills	- Problem solving	- Thinking Differer	•
SOIT SKIIIS	- Communication skills	- Planning	- Teamwork

WORK EXPERIENCE

03.2023 - 01.2024

Al Scientist - Intern | Ipazia, Milan, Italy.

Deep Learning of Portfolio Optimization

- analysed large-scale time-series datasets on AWS and developed a deep learning model with LSTM using PyTorch Lightning to directly optimise portfolio Sharpe ratio.
- currently engaged in pioneering research to develop a novel architecture, incorporating Hopfield layers and Transformers by positional encoding time-series data, while contributing to a scikit library.
- visualised portfolio results by comparing weight allocations with benchmark portfolios, in addition to equity curve analysis and portfolio metrics.

11.2022 - 03.2023

Master's Thesis Student | University of Padova, Italy.

Real Space Renormalization Group Techniques for lattice systems.

• conducted extensive study of 4 real-space renormalization group methods applied to Ising and Potts models on lattices.

• implemented Monte Carlo method for renormalization group using the efficient Wulff cluster sampling algorithm.

11.2018 - 07.2019

Master's Thesis Student | *Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru.*

Phase-Field Modelling of Eutectoid Transformation in Ternary systems.

- developed a C program that utilizes numerical methods to solve a one-dimensional sharp interface model with a Stefan boundary condition.
- analysed the variation of the growth constant by solving the model for 10 different supersaturation values.

11.2017 - 05.2018

Bachelor's Thesis Student | *Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru.*

Triple point fermions in Full-Heusler compounds using first principle calculations.

- enhanced proficiency in Linux operating systems and command-line interfaces.
- utilized Cray supercomputer clusters and software packages: VASP, WannierTools, Phonopy to compute energy band diagrams and check stability of compounds.
- identified 7 new compounds with triple point fermions.
- presented progress updates every week in the lab group meetings.

EDUCATION

10.2019 - 07.2023	Master's degree in Physics University of Padova, Italy.
08.2018 - 07.2019	Master of Science in Materials Science Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru
08.2014 - 05.2018	Bachelor of Science (Research) in Materials Science Indian Institute of Science

PROJECTS

12.2023 - 01.2024

Corporate Credit Rating Forecast using Machine Learning Methods

- Implemented machine learning models, including XGBoost and RandomForest, to predict corporate credit ratings from historical financial data.
- Applied techniques such as SMOTE to address class imbalance in datasets, and hyperparameter optimisation to improve the classification models.
- Gained proficiency in financial ratios and understand a company's fiscal strength.